Inventory of the Narodno-trudovoi soiuz samizdat collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Narodno-trudovoi soiuz samizdat collection
1960-1991
2000C83
Hoover Institution Archives
73 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 card file box (33.8 linear feet)
The collection contains novels, poems, and articles submitted for publication, as well as periodicals, pamphlets, speeches and writings, press releases, statements, petitions, photographs, slides, films, and sound recordings, published or circulated by underground and uncensored presses or groups in the Soviet Union, relating to political and cultural conditions in the Soviet Union and collected by the Narodno-trudovoi soiuz. Sound use copies of sound recordings available.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Boxes 1-72 stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
The most complete collection of samizdat in the West is the Arkhiv Samizdata of the Research Department of Radio Liberty in Munich (now at the Open Society Archives in Budapest). However, that collection does not include poetry, novels and other literature widely represented in the Hoover Institution Archives Narodno-trudovoi soiuz samizdat collection.
M. Baranovich papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Suetnov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Narodno-trudovoi soiuz declaration, Hoover Institution Archives
Constantin W. Boldyreff papers, Hoover Institution Archives
George Miller-Kurakin papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Sergej Utechin interviews, Hoover Institution Archives
B. Prianishnikov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
Narodno-trudovoi soiuz (National Alliance of Russian Solidarists, known by its Russian abbreviation "NTS") was founded in 1930 by a group of young Russian "White émigrés" in Serbia. As a Russian patriotic, anticommunist organization, the NTS fought communism by studying Soviet culture to understand the soul of people living in the USSR. It is the largest and most active political association of Russian émigrés in Western Germany.
Beginning in 1945, the NTS published the monthly magazine Posev and the literary review Grani, often featuring anti-Soviet samizdat literature smuggled from the USSR.
Samizdat is dissident literature written by Soviet citizens that would not be accepted by Soviet authorities for publication in the USSR. The name Samizdat combines the word sam (self, by oneself), and izdat, the abbreviation of izdatel'stvo (Publishing house). Such literature was available only as handwritten or typewritten copies, distributed secretly among trusted people.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains novels, poems, and articles submitted for publication, as well as periodicals, pamphlets, speeches and writings, press releases, statements, petitions, photographs, slides, film, and sound recordings, related to political, social, and economic conditions in the Soviet Union and collected by the Narodno-trudovoi soiuz.
Samizdat documents that were created in the former Soviet Union reflect the interests and activities of dissidents. The materials were smuggled abroad for publication in the West and collected by the NTS publishing house Posev.
The materials were cataloged by NTS. As of 31 March 2000 more then 3442 documents were arranged by serial number roughly in chronological order by the date of arrival, although not all documents here are numbered.
The materials are arranged by the numbering system assigned by NTS. Each number consists of two components: a number assigned sequentially and a year of creation in two-digit abbreviation (ie. 1968 would be 68). For example, number 139/66 is the 139 document acquired, which dates from 1966. Not all sequential numbers are included in the collection and the material is not in exact chronological order.
The date of arrival at NTS is later than the date of document creation since it took some time to deliver the materials to the West. The title, type of document, physical form, and information on publication may be found in the NTS item catalog. Items without numbers are listed by title at the end of the numerical sequence.
The materials were arranged in two categories by NTS: Samizdat and Oversize samizdat. The Hoover Institution separated other formats for preservation. Now the materials are arranged by size and physical form and are divided into four categories: (1) Samizdat files, (2) Oversize samizdat files, (3) Film, slides, and negatives (4) Sound recordings.
An itemized list in Russian matching the item number with a title and other information created by NTS and updated by Hoover Institution staff may be found in the appendix.
Arrangement
Records are arranged as originally received from the organization; generally by the Narodno-trudovoi soiuz number. Each number consists of two components: a number assigned sequentially and a year in two-digit abbreviation (ie. 1968 would be 68). For example, number 139/66 is the 139th document, which dates from 1966. Not all sequential numbers are included in the collection and the material is not in exact chronological order.
Narodno-trudovoi soiuz.; Censorship--Soviet Union.; Phonotapes.; Soviet Union--Civilization.; Soviet Union--History--1953-1985.; Soviet Union--History--1985-1991.; Underground literature--Soviet Union.
- Samizdat files, 1960-1991. (Box 1-53.)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains novels, poems, articles, periodicals, statements, petitions, and press releases. Arranged by NTS number (each NTS number consists of two components: a number assigned sequentially and a year of creation in two-digit abbreviation) Not all sequential numbers are in the collection, and the material is not in exact chronological order. An itemized list in Russian matching the item number with a title and other information created by NTS and updated by Hoover Institution staff may be found in the Appendix.
  - Index of files (Box 1)
  - 1/67-8/67 (Box 1)
  - 9/65-11/65 (Box 1)
  - 12/66-32/66 (Box 1)
  - 33/65-34/65 (Box 1)
  - 35/66 (Box 1)
  - 36/64-55/64 (Box 1)
  - 56/66-62/66 (Box 1)
  - 63/67-66/67 (Box 1)
  - 67/64 (Box 1)
  - 68/63. (Box 1)
    General note
    See box 66
  - 69/66-79/66 (Box 1)
  - 80/67-90/67 (Box 1)
  - 91/66-96/66 (Box 1)
  - 97/67. (Box 1)
    See also boxes 66 and 73
  - 98/67-101/67 (Box 1)
  - 102/66-103/66 (Box 1)
  - 104/65-112/65 (Box 1)
  - 113/67-115/67 (Box 1)
  - 119/67-138/67 (Box 1)
  - 139/66-142/66 (Box 1)
  - 146/66-153/66 (Box 2)
  - 154/67-155/67 (Box 2)
  - 156/66-193/66 (Box 2)
  - 194/64-196/64 (Box 2)
  - 197/67-198/67 (Box 2)
  - 199/60 (Box 2)
  - 200/67 (Box 2)
  - 201/66 (Box 2)
  - 203/66 (Box 2)
  - 204/67-206/67 (Box 2)
  - 208/67 (Box 2)
  - 210/66-212/66 (Box 2)
  - 213/66-214/66 (Box 2)
  - 222/66. (Box 2)
    See box 71
  - 223/66. (Box 2)
    See box 72
  - 226/66 (Box 2)
  - 227/64-232/64 (Box 2)
  - 233/65-234/65 (Box 2)
  - 235/67-255/67 (Box 2)
  - 256/67-262/67 (Box 3)
  - 264/67-268/67 (Box 3)
  - 275/68 (Box 3)
  - 277/68-278/68 (Box 3)
  - 279/67-280/67 (Box 3)
  - 284/68-304/68 (Box 3)
  - 308/68-311/68 (Box 3)
  - 347/68-349/68 (Box 3)
  - 352/68-356/68 (Box 3)
  - 357/68 (Box 3)
  - 360/68-369/68 (Box 3)
  - 377/68-379/68 (Box 3)
  - 380/68 (Box 4)
  - 382/68-384/68 (Box 4)
  - 386/68-394/68 (Box 4)
  - 396/68-398/68 (Box 4)
  - 403/68-407/68 (Box 4)
  - 409/69-415/69 (Box 4)
  - 416/69. (Box 4)
    See 556/70
  - 417/69-420/69 (Box 4)
  - 422/69-424/69 (Box 4)
  - 425/69 (Box 5)
  - 426/69. (Box 5)
    See box 61
  - 427/69-446/69 (Box 5)
  - 448/68-449/68 (Box 5)
  - 450/69-461/69 (Box 5)
  - 463/68 (Box 5)
  - 464/69-469/69 (Box 5)
  - 470/68 (Box 5)
  - 471/69-485/69 (Box 5)
  - 488/69-490/69 (Box 5)
  - 491/69-492/69 (Box 6)
  - 494/69-502/69 (Box 6)
  - 504/69-507/69 (Box 6)
  - 508/69. (Box 6)
    See box 65
  - 509/69-511/69 (Box 6)
  - 513/69 (Box 6)
  - 524/69 (Box 6)
  - 526/69-530/69 (Box 6)
  - 531/69. (Box 6)
    See also box 75
  - 532/69 (Box 6)
  - 533/? (Box 6)
  - 534/63 (Box 6)
  - 535/66-539/66 (Box 6)
  - 541/69 (Box 6)
  - 544/70-550/70 (Box 6)
  - 552/70 (Box 6)
  - 554/70 (Box 6)
  - 556/70 (Box 6)
  - 558/70. (Box 6)
    See also box 76
  - 559/70 (Box 6)
  - 561/70 (Box 7)
  - 563/70-567/70 (Box 7)
  - 573/70 (Box 7)
  - 577/70-578/70 (Box 7)
  - 579/66-582/66 (Box 7)
  - 583/70-592/70 (Box 7)
  - 593/70. (Box 7)
    See boxes 64 and 73
  - 596/70-598/70 (Box 7)
  - 600/70-604/70 (Box 7)
  - 606/70-611/70 (Box 7)
  - 611a/73 (Box 7)
  - 611b/71 (Box 7)
  - 611v/76 (Box 7)
  - 612/70 (Box 7)
  - 613/70. (Box 7)
    See boxes 68 and 73
  - 614/70-623/70 (Box 7)
  - 626/70-630/70 (Box 7)
  - 631/70-637/70 (Box 8)
  - 639/70. (Box 8)
    See also box 65
  - 640/70-645/70 (Box 8)
  - 647/70 (Box 8)
  - 648/71. (Box 8)
  - 649/71-659/71 (Box 8)
  - 661/71-666/71 (Box 8)
  - 668/71-670/71 (Box 8)
  - 671/71. (Box 8)
  - 672/71. (Box 8)
  - 673/71. (Box 8)
    See box 73
  - 674/71. (Box 8)
  - 675/71-679/71. (Box 8)
    See boxes 66, 73, and 76
  - 680/71. (Box 8)
    See boxes 64, 66, 67, and 73
  - 681/71-685/71 (Box 8)
  - 687/71 (Box 8)
  - 689/71 (Box 8)
  - 690/70 (Box 8)
  - 691/71 (Box 8)
  - 692/71 (Box 9)
  - 693/71. (Box 9)
  - 702/72-703/72 (Box 9)
  - 705/72-706/72 (Box 9)
  - 707/72. (Box 9)
    See boxes 55 and 56
  - 708/72 (Box 9)
  - 709/72-710/72. (Box 9)
    See box 59
  - 711/72 (Box 9)
  - 712/72. (Box 9)
    See box 60
  - 713/72 (Box 9)
  - 716/72. (Box 9)
    See box 76
  - 717/72-724/72. (Box 9)
    See also box 73
  - 732/73 (Box 9)
  - 734/73. (Box 9)
  - 735/73-738/73 (Box 9)
  - 739/73-740/73. (Box 9)
  - 744/73 (Box 9)
  - 746/73 (Box 9)
  - 749/73-750/73 (Box 9)
  - 751/73. (Box 9)
  - 752/73-757/73. (Box 9)
    See boxes 56 and 76
  - 758/73. (Box 9)
  - 759/73-760/73. (Box 9)
    See boxes 54 and 76
  - 761/73. (Box 9)
  - 762/73-766/73. (Box 10)
  - 767/73 (Box 10)
  - 781/73 (Box 10)
  - 788/74-792/74 (Box 10)
  - 793/74. (Box 10)
  - 794/74-795/74 (Box 10)
  - 796/74. (Box 10)
    See boxes 54, 76 and 77
  - 797/74. (Box 10)
    See box 56 and 76
  - 798/74 (Box 10)
  - 799/74. (Box 10)
    See boxes 54, 58 and 75
  - 801/74-809/74 (Box 10)
  - 815/74. (Box 10)
    See boxes 63 and 76
  - 817/74. (Box 10)
    See boxes 58 and 75
  - 819/74. (Box 10)
    See boxes 75 and 76
  - 821/74-821a/74. (Box 10)
    See box 75
  - 823/74-830/74 (Box 10)
  - 832/74-834/74 (Box 10)
  - 835/74. (Box 10)
  - 836/74 (Box 10)
  - 837/74. (Box 10)
    See 829/74
  - 838/74-844/74 (Box 10)
  - 845/75 (Box 10)
  - 846/74-856/74 (Box 11)
  - 858/74-862/74 (Box 11)
  - 863/75-865/75 (Box 11)
  - 867/75. (Box 11)
  - 868/75. (Box 11)
  - 869/75-880/75 (Box 11)
  - 881/75-883/75. (Box 11)
    See box 57
  - 887/75 (Box 11)
  - 888/75-889/75. (Box 11)
  - 890/75-891/75 (Box 11)
  - 892/75-895/75. (Box 11)
  - 896/75 (Box 11)
  - 897/75-898/75 (Box 12)
  - 902/75-903/75 (Box 12)
  - 905/75-908/75 (Box 12)
  - 910/75-914/75 (Box 12)
  - 916/75 (Box 12)
  - 924/76 (Box 12)
  - 925/76. (Box 12)
    See boxes 55 and 76
  - 926/76-946/76 (Box 12)
  - 948/76-956/76 (Box 12)
  - 957/76. (Box 12)
  - 958/76 (Box 12)
  - 960/76-961/76 (Box 12)
  - 964/76 (Box 12)
  - 965/77-975/77 (Box 13)
  - 978/77-982/77. (Box 13)
  - 983/77 (Box 13)
  - 984/77-986/77. (Box 13)
  - 997/77 (Box 13)
  - 998/77. (Box 13)
  - 999/77 (Box 13)
  - 1000/77-1003/77. (Box 13)
  - 1004/77-1008/77. (Box 14)
  - 1009/77-1013/77 (Box 14)
  - 1014/77. (Box 14)
    See box 55
  - 1015/77-1019/77 (Box 14)
  - 1020/77. (Box 14)
    See boxes 68 and 76
  - 1021/77-1026/77 (Box 14)
  - 1027/77. (Box 14)
    See box 58
  - 1028/77-1043/77 (Box 14)
  - 1045/77-1047/77 (Box 14)
  - 1048/78-1054/78 (Box 14)
  - 1055/78-1056/78. (Box 15)
  - 1057/78. (Box 15)
    See boxes 62 and 73
  - 1058/78. (Box 15)
  - 1059/78 (Box 15)
  - 1061/78. (Box 15)
    See also box 63
  - 1062/78-1067/78 (Box 15)
  - 1068/78 (Box 15)
  - 1069/78-1071/78. (Box 15)
  - 1072/78. (Box 15)
    See also box 74
  - 1073/78-1075/78 (Box 15)
  - 1076/78. (Box 15)
    See also box74
  - 1077/78-1082/78 (Box 15)
  - 1085/78-1088/78 (Box 15)
  - 1091/78-1094/78 (Box 15)
  - 1095/78-1102/78 (Box 16)
  - 1104/78-1108/78 (Box 16)
  - 1109/79 (Box 16)
  - 1112/79-1115/79 (Box 16)
  - 1118/79-1138/79 (Box 16)
  - 1141/79 (Box 16)
  - 1147/79-1448/82. (Box 16)
  - 1449/79-1152/79 (Box 16)
  - 1153/78 (Box 16)
  - 1154/?-1157/? (Box 16)
  - 1158/79 (Box 16)
  - 1160/79-1170/79 (Box 16)
  - 1171/79. (Box 17)
    See box 62
  - 1172/79 (Box 17)
  - 1173/79. (Box 17)
  - 1174/79-1197/79 (Box 17)
  - 1198/79-1213/79 (Box 18)
  - 1216/79-1217/79 (Box 18)
  - 1219/79. (Box 18)
  - 1220-1222/79 (Box 18)
  - 1223/80-1247/80 (Box 18)
  - 1249/80-1260/80 (Box 18)
  - (Box 18)
  - 1261/80-1272/80 (Box 19)
  - 1273/80. (Box 19)
  - 1274/80 (Box 19)
  - 1276/80-1280/80 (Box 19)
  - 1282/80-1287/80 (Box 19)
  - 1290/80 (Box 19)
  - 1294/80 (Box 19)
  - 1295/80. (Box 19)
  - 1296/80. (Box 19)
  - 1297/80 (Box 19)
  - 1298/81-1302/81 (Box 19)
  - 1303/81. (Box 19)
  - 1305/81-1308/81 (Box 20)
  - 1309/81. (Box 20)
  - 1310/81-1314/81 (Box 20)
  - 1315/81. (Box 20)
  - 1316/81. (Box 20)
    See box 74
  - 1317/81-1328/81 (Box 20)
  - 1329/81-1331/81. (Box 20)
  - 1332/81-1336/81 (Box 20)
  - 1337/81. (Box 20)
  - 1338/81-1341/81. (Box 20)
  - 1342/81-1343/81. (Box 20)
  - 1344/81 (Box 20)
  - 1345/81. (Box 20)
  - 1346/61 (Box 20)
  - 1347/81. (Box 20)
  - 1348/81 (Box 20)
  - 1349/81-1351/81 (Box 21)
  - 1352/81. (Box 21)
  - 1353/81-1354/81 (Box 21)
  - 1355/81-1356/81. (Box 21)
  - 1357/82-1374/82 (Box 21)
  - 1377/82-1378/82. (Box 21)
  - 1379/82. (Box 21)
  - 1380/82 (Box 21)
  - 1381/82-1384/2. (Box 21)
  - 1385/82-1391/82 (Box 21)
  - 1392/82. (Box 21)
  - 1393/82-1394/82. (Box 21)
    See also boxes 59 and 74
  - 1395/82 (Box 21)
  - 1396/82. (Box 21)
  - 1397/82 (Box 21)
  - 1398/82. (Box 21)
  - 1399/82-1404/82 (Box 21)
  - 1409/82-1413/82 (Box 21)
  - 1414/82. (Box 21)
  - 1415/82 (Box 22)
  - 1416/82-1422/82. (Box 22)
  - 1423/82-1426/82 (Box 22)
  - 1427/82. (Box 22)
  - 1428/82-1433/82 (Box 22)
  - 1435/82-1440/82 (Box 22)
  - 1441/82. (Box 22)
    See also box 77
  - 1442/82-1446/82 (Box 22)
  - 1447/82-1448/82. (Box 22)
  - 1477/82-1478/82 (Box 22)
  - 1480/82 (Box 22)
  - 1481/83 (Box 22)
  - 1482/83. (Box 22)
    See box 77
  - 1483/83-1499/83 (Box 22)
  - 1500/83-1504/83. (Box 22)
    See boxes 63 and 74
  - 1504A/83. (Box 22)
  - 1505/83-1507/83. (Box 22)
  - 1508/83-1509/83 (Box 22)
  - 1511/83-1515/83 (Box 23)
  - 1518/83-1541A/83 (Box 23)
  - 1541B/83. (Box 23)
  - 1542/83 (Box 23)
  - 1543/83-1549/83 (Box 24)
  - 1550/84-1559/84 (Box 24)
  - 1560/84. (Box 24)
  - 1561/84-1572/84 (Box 24)
  - 1574/84-1583/84 (Box 24)
  - 1584/84-1593/84 (Box 25)
  - 1594/85 (Box 25)
  - 1595/85. (Box 25)
  - 1596/85-1610/85 (Box 25)
  - 1611/85-1613/85. (Box 25)
  - 1614/85. (Box 25)
  - 1615/85-1621/85 (Box 25)
  - 1622/85. (Box 25)
  - 1623/85-1629/85 (Box 25)
  - 1630/85-1632/85 (Box 26)
  - 1634/85-1643/85 (Box 26)
  - 1645/85-1658/85 (Box 26)
  - 1659/85. (Box 26)
  - 1660/85-1668/85 (Box 26)
  - 1669/85. (Box 26)
  - 1670/85. (Box 26)
  - 1671/86-1673/86 (Box 26)
  - 1675/86 (Box 26)
  - 1676/86. (Box 26)
  - 1677/86 (Box 26)
  - 1678/77 (Box 26)
  - 1679/79. (Box 26)
    See box 67
  - 1680/86 (Box 26)
  - 1681/84. (Box 26)
  - 1682/86. (Box 26)
  - 1683/86. (Box 26)
  - 1684/86-1686/86 (Box 27)
  - 1687/86. (Box 27)
  - 1688/86-1696/86 (Box 27)
  - 1697/87-1700/87 (Box 27)
  - 1701/87. (Box 27)
  - 1702/87. (Box 27)
  - 1703/84 (Box 27)
  - 1704/87-1726/87 (Box 27)
  - 1727/87-1729/87. (Box 27)
  - 1730/87-1731/87 (Box 27)
  - 1732/87-1733/87. (Box 27)
  - 1743/87-1740/87 (Box 27)
  - 1741/87-1773/87 (Box 28)
  - 1775/87-1784/87 (Box 28)
  - 1787/88-1797/88 (Box 28)
  - 1798/88-1799/88 (Box 29)
  - 1800/88. (Box 29)
  - 1801/88-1804/88 (Box 29)
  - 1806/88-1808/88 (Box 29)
  - 1809/88. (Box 29)
  - 1810/88 (Box 29)
  - 1812/88-1859/99 (Box 29)
  - 1861/88-1869/88 (Box 29)
  - 1870/88-1875/88 (Box 30)
  - 1877/88-1919/88 (Box 30)
  - 1920/88-1950/88 (Box 31)
  - 1951/88. (Box 31)
  - 1952/88-1957/88 (Box 31)
  - 1958A/81 (Box 31)
  - 1958B/82 (Box 31)
  - 1959/88-1966/88 (Box 31)
  - 1967/88-1979/88 (Box 32)
  - 1980/88-1997/88. (Box 32)
  - 1998/88-2012/88 (Box 32)
  - 2014/88-2051/88 (Box 33)
  - 2052/88-2064/88 (Box 34)
  - 2066/88-2094/88 (Box 34)
  - 2095/88-2115/88 (Box 35)
  - 2116/88. (Box 35)
  - 2117/88-2143/88 (Box 35)
  - 2144/89-2152/89 (Box 35)
  - 2155/89 (Box 35)
  - 2157/88-2165/89 (Box 35)
  - 2166/89-2168/89 (Box 36)
  - 2169/82-2172/89. (Box 36)
  - 2174/89 (Box 36)
  - 2177/89-2190/89 (Box 36)
  - 2192/89-2198/89 (Box 36)
  - 2199/89-2210/89. (Box 36)
  - 2211/89-2259/89 (Box 37)
  - 2260/89-2261/89. (Box 37)
  - 2263/89. (Box 37)
  - 2264/89-2270/89 (Box 37)
  - 2272/89-2280/89 (Box 37)
  - 2182/89-2301/89 (Box 38)
  - 2302/89. (Box 38)
  - 2303/89-2308/89 (Box 38)
  - 2309/89. (Box 38)
  - 2310/89-2315/89 (Box 38)
  - 2316/89-2345/89 (Box 39)
  - 2347/89-2369/89 (Box 39)
  - 2370/89-2430/89 (Box 40)
  - 2431/89-2462/89 (Box 41)
  - 2463/89. (Box 41)
  - 2466/89-2499/89 (Box 41)
  - 2500/89-2503/89 (Box 42)
  - 2505/89-2575/89 (Box 42)
  - 2577/89-2603/89 (Box 43)
  - 2604/89. (Box 43)
  - 2605/89-2647/89 (Box 43)
  - 2649/90-2653/90 (Box 43)
  - 2654/90-2728/90 (Box 44)
  - 2729/90-2792/90 (Box 45)
  - 2793/90. (Box 45)
  - 2794/90-2799/90 (Box 45)
  - 2800/90-2808/90. (Box 45)
  - 2809/90-2887/90 (Box 46)
  - 2888/90-2961/90 (Box 47)
  - 2962/90-3023/90 (Box 48)
  - 3024/90-3110/90 (Box 49)
  - 3111/90. (Box 49)
  - 3112/90-3192/90 (Box 50)
  - 3193/90-3216/90 (Box 51)
  - 3218/90-3245/90 (Box 51)
  - 3246/90. (Box 51)
  - 3247/90-3288/90 (Box 51)
  - 3289/90-3360/90 (Box 52)
  - 3361/91-3442/91 (Box 53)
- Oversize samizdat files, 1963-1990. (Box 54-72.)
  Materials separated from the main group of materials and designated "oversize" by NTS. Includes manuscripts, photocopies, and printed matter. Arranged by format for preservation, for the numerical and title list see: http://media.hoover.org/documents/NTSsamizdat_0.pdf.
  - 759/73 (Box 54)
  - 760/73 (Box 54)
  - 796/74 (Box 54)
  - 799/74. (Box 54)
    See also boxes 58 and 75
  - 707/72 (Box 55)
  - 925/76. (Box 55)
  - 1014/77 (Box 55)
  - 707/72 (Box 56)
  - 752/73-755/73 (Box 56)
  - 797/74 (Box 56)
  - 881/75-883/75 (Box 57)
  - 1447/82 (Box 57)
  - 1448/82 (Box 57)
  - 1560/84 (Box 57)
  - 1669/85 (Box 57)
  - 817/74 (Box 58)
  - 799/74. (Box 58)
    See also boxes 55 and 75
  - 1027/77 (Box 58)
  - 1273/80 (Box 58)
  - 1541B/83 (Box 58)
  - 1670/85 (Box 58)
  - 709/72 (Box 59)
  - 710/72 (Box 59)
  - 1393/82 (Box 59)
  - 1800/88 (Box 59)
  - 712/72 (Box 60)
  - 1687/86 (Box 60)
  - 1296/80 (Box 60)
  - 426/68 (Box 61)
  - 1303/61 (Box 61)
  - 1309/81 (Box 61)
  - 1173/79 (Box 61)
  - 1681/84 (Box 61)
  - 2263/89 (Box 61)
  - 2260/89 (Box 62)
  - 2261/89 (Box 62)
  - 2463/89 (Box 62)
  - 2302/89 (Box 62)
  - 1295/80 (Box 62)
  - 1171/79 (Box 62)
  - 815/74 (Box 63)
  - 1500/83-1507/83 (Box 63)
  - 1057/78. (Box 63)
  - 1061/78 (Box 63)
  - 593/70. (Box 64)
  - 680/71. (Box 64)
    See also boxes 66, 67, and 73
  - 3246/90 (Box 65)
  - 3111/90 (Box 65)
  - 693/71 (Box 65)
  - 508/69 (Box 65)
  - 639/70 (Box 65)
  - 671/71 (Box 65)
  - 97/67 (Box 66)
  - 68/63 (Box 66)
  - 648/71 (Box 66)
  - 675/71-680/71 (Box 66)
  - 1679/79 (Box 67)
  - 680/71. (Box 67)
    See also boxes 64, 66 and 73
  - 1020/77 (Box 68)
  - 613/70. (Box 68)
  - "ADRIAN-ein deutsches Märchen," by Hasso Laudon, 1968 (Box 68)
  - "Cheshskii samizdat,", 1969 (Box 68)
  - "Otzyv na Odin Den' Ivana Denisovicha," by anonymous author, 1963 (Box 68)
  - "Konets puti Vasiliia Nikitenkova," by anonymous author, 1971 (Box 69)
  - Magazine articles, by Mark Popovskii, 1977 (Box 69)
  - "Khristos v nashi dni, v Rossii..," by Dmitrii Dudko, 1975 (Box 69)
  - "Preodolenie soblaznov," by Dmitrii Dudko, 1975 (Box 69)
  - "Da voskresnet Bog," by Dmitrii Dudko, 1969 (Box 69)
  - "Stikhi iz Rossii,", 1983 (Box 69)
  - "Rossiiskie vedomosti," #8-12, 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Vozrozhdenie," bulletin, #24, Nizhnii Tagil, 1989 (Box 70)
  - "Otkrytoe pis'mo," ierodiakon Dionisii, 1987 (Box 70)
  - "Russkoe Slovo,", 1966 (Box 70)
  - "Latviia," Latviiskoe Nezavisimoe Infomatsionnoe Agenstvo, bulletin, 1988 (Box 70)
  - Peterburgskii Monarkhicheskii Tsentr, programma, 1990 (Box 70)
  - "Golos Truda," "Russkoe Delo," Konfederatsiia Anarkho-Sindikalistov, Novosibirsk, 1990 (Box 70)
  - "Nasha pozitsiia," Demokraticheskaia partiia Rossii, 1989 (Box 70)
  - "Ustav Natsional'no-demokraticheskoi organizatsii "Svobodnaia Rossiia,", 1990 (Box 70)
  - "Sovetskaia tragediia," by anonymous author, 1998 (Box 70)
  - "Pliuralizm sk orostei," by Viktor Vinokurov, Grigorii Starunov, and others, Ul'ianovsk, 1990 (Box 70)
  - "Stikhi," by Viktor Bozhii, M. Bestuzhev, and Il'ia Bokshtein, 1962-1968 (Box 70)
  - "Demoktaticheskii tsentr," listovka, 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Vsesoiuznyi sovet mnogodetnykh semei," proposals, 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Gorod na plakhe," by Mikhail Zotov, 1988 (Box 70)
  - "K predstoiashchei avgustovskoi konferentsii," press-tsentr "Obshchina,", 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Ob otnoshenii k partii "Demokraticheskii soiuz,", 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Printsipy organizatsii i osnovnye tseli "Narodnogo Fronta,", 1988 (Box 70)
  - Informatsionnoe Agentstvo SMOT, bulletin #7, June 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Roman gazeta," informatsionnoe prilozhenie, #2, Leningrad, 1988 (Box 70)
  - "Gosudarstvennomy Sekretariu SSHa g-nu Shultsu," 1987, appeal from Zviad Gamsaxurdia (Box 70)
    Includes other documents related to civil rights in Georgia
  - 222/66 (Box 71)
  - 223/66 (Box 72)
- Film, slides, and negatives, 1969-1990. (Box 73-76)
  Contains films, slides, and negatives. Arranged by physical form, then by NTS number.
  Access
  Please note that not all of this material is immediately accessible. To view the material in this series during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see.
  Alternate Forms Available
  Items listed in this section with a "See also" note are available as paper copies in the box number listed. The paper copies were received by the Hoover Archives along with the photographic materials. The Hoover Archives is not able to verify that the paper copies duplicate every image contained in the photographic version of the same item.
  Some of the photographic items were digitized by the Hoover Archives and are available on workstations in the reading room. Due to their physical condition the photographic materials are extremely difficult to digitize, so relatively few have been digitized.
  - Film, 1976-1990 (Box 73-75)
    - 1-7 (Box 73)
    - 97/67. (Box 73)
      See also box 66
    - 593/70. (Box 73)
      See also box 64
    - 613/70. (Box 73)
      See also box 68
    - 673/71 (Box 73)
    - 676/71. (Box 73)
    - 680/71. (Box 73)